Hey, hey,
hey, hey.
Good morning everyone and welcome to the
Fiber Broadband Association's Fire for
Breakfast. We're now in our ninth
episode of 2026. The gold sponsor for
Fiber Breakfast is Condex. You know,
Congress is in session this week and
yesterday the Senate Commerce Committee
held a hearing titled Less Hype, More
Help: AI that Improves Safety,
Productivity, and Care. It was convened
by US Senator Ted Bud from North
Carolina. He's chairman of the
subcommittee on science, manufacturing,
and competitiveness. And the hearing
explored how AI technology as
transformative as the internet is
improving Americans quality of life,
creating jobs, driving economic growth
with witnesses sharing real world
success stories in safety, productivity,
and healthcare. In the House, the farm
bill is currently being marked up in the
House Agricultural Committee with
leadership aiming for a floor vote
before the Easter recess. We appreciate
the current draft language funds and
codifies the USDA's Reconnect program.
Uh but the Fiber Broadband Association
is encouraging bipartisan Reconnect
America Act include in this legislation
that establishes 100 by 100 megabit
symmetric service versus the draft
language of 50 meg by 24. I don't know
where that came from, but it's crazy.
Um, so we want to make sure that rural
America receives the connectivity it
deserves. And at NTIA, we're now at 52
out of the 56 final proposals have been
approved. So, we're getting there and uh
making the significant progress in
moving the program forward. Following
approvals from NIST, 23 states have
countersigned their NTIM agreements and
officially begun contracting process
with subgrantees. So, this is moving
very quickly.
NTI is expected to release its B
non-eployment notice for the remaining
$21 billion on March 11th. Uh so
forthcoming guidance should clarify the
allowable uses for non-eployment funds
and provide directions and how the state
AI laws may impact eligibility for
accessing those funds. And last week on
Five for Breakfast, our guest was our
good buddy Ernesto Falcon uh from the
California PUC who discussed broadband
competit competitiveness and pricing
strategies in California urban markets.
The PUC's latest study found that if
each of the major cities in California
had multi- gigabit broadband providers,
it would save Californians over a
billion dollars a year in their
broadband service. So if you miss that,
you can go back into our website and
watch the replay. Today on Fire for
Breakfast, our guest is the Fiber
Broadband Association's former chairman
and current treasurer, Jimmy Todd, the
CEO of Next. He's going to discuss
getting a front row seat to the telecom
evolution 75 years in the making. Uh
Jimmy is general manager and CEO of Next
and brings 40 years of experience and
technology and communications. And under
Jimmy's leadership, NexTech has evolved
from a rural cooperative telephone
company into a leading communications
and technology provider, pioneering
fiber the home in rural America, now
delivering broadband across 11,000
square miles in Kansas. He oversees
strategic growth, innovation, and
diversification, including advanced data
center services, and nationwide
technical support. A recognized advocate
for telecommunications, fiber broadband,
Jimmy's served on numerous boards and
committee including the Kansas Fiber
Network, Nextec Wireless, W2ATA,
NT, NTCA, NRTC, NCSC, a lot of N
acronyms. US Telecom and the Fiber
Broadband Association. He was appointed
to the FCC's precision a task force and
beyond leadership uh industry
leadership. Jimmy actively contributes
to local and state initiatives to
various boards. Jimmy's undergraduate
education was at Oxford College of Emory
University and Chapman University. He
earned his MBA through the University of
Portland. And Jimmy's also a veteran
serving 10 years in the US Navy and 11
years in the US Army and Army National
Guard. So, thank you Jimmy for your
service not only for our nation and our
military but also for the Fiber
Broadband Association. you've been just
a tremendous force in kind of driving
our industry. So, thank you for that.
>> So, audience,
>> please type in your questions. Go and
we'll work those in discussion. So,
Jimmy is like one of my favorite people.
So, I've definitely been looking forward
to this discussion. Not that we don't
talk every day, but uh so welcome Jimmy.
>> Thanks Gary.
you know, we we were just talking about,
you know, when you were chairman, you
know, the chairman's keynote has kind of
become uh a you know, competition and uh
you know, with JJ kind of setting the
bar and then you rode in the big dog.
So, tell us a little bit about uh you
were just telling me what did you do
7,500 miles in August last year on on
your motorcycles?
>> Yes, sir. um got the opportunity. Well,
of course, you know, I rode the chopper
up to the Sturgeist Rally, but after
that, I had a little cross-country
venture that that uh took me from Kansas
to West Virginia, all the way down to
South Carolina, up to Maryland, over to
New Jersey, up to Toronto, over to uh
Portsouth, New Hampshire, and and then
Colorado Springs before coming home. So,
it was a it was a good ride.
>> Well, more power to you. Um, I don't
know that I can handle a motorcycle ride
all those miles.
So, how's Miss Shirley doing?
>> Doing well. Uh, it's uh it's that year
time of year where the sniffles and
stuff happen. She's been doing some
subbing at uh the local uh junior high
and grade schools and so of course she's
got to, you know, have the opportunity
to work through that. But, uh, she's
she's doing great. Thanks for asking.
Well, next tech uh just amazing company.
75 years. That's uh really impressive to
you know any business that can um
survive and evolve and be able to thrive
in 75 years. So when you look back what
would be the most defining moment or
decision and really set the trajectory
for the company's growth and staying
power?
>> You know there's there's a couple of
points Gary. I say at the very beginning
it was a commitment to serve in an area
that others wouldn't serve and through
that that's how rural telephone the
parent of Nexttec got started bringing
uh communications telephone
communications to very rural areas but
then you you look forward and our
engagement into fiber is is probably the
thing that really changed the game for
us. Um, now about the same time that we
were bringing fi, you know, we were the
first to bring fiber to a rural
community as as a as a means to provide
connectivity for for telecom and and
other services. You know, we were also
the first in the country to to
competitively serve in another market.
And so, you know, we we have a history
of of kind of being out there on the
edge, but I do believe when you kind of
look at our evolution
since the '9s, it has been, you know, a
fiber-based network that has put us in a
position uh to continue to evolve with
the technology that has changed quite
dramatically in in the past 30 years.
So when you u look at you know for some
of the folks that don't know next tech's
story um can you kind of just provide a
rough timeline of you know going from
the small telephone cooperative and to
kind of where you are today?
>> Sure. you know, uh
we got started in in 51 and through um
acquiring exchanges um rural exchanges
and buying some of those from some of
the larger providers who were were not
investing. We we built the cooperative
footprint which you know extends across
the northwest and north central part of
the state. And as we uh continued to
build out those communities and provide
the connectivity across those
communities, that's when we started uh
transitioning um into to the fiber. So
through the 70s, we were still acquiring
exchanges um from like Southwestern Bell
and and Sprint United. And then you know
in the 80s we started that transition in
into fiber um and and moving our step
switches to electronic switches which
eventually became IPbased uh switches.
You know all of that technology you know
really started advancing significantly
in the 80s and through the 90s. And of
course the 90s is when we brought fiber
to the home in in a rural community. And
so when you kind of look at that, that
was kind of an evolution into the
original building. through uh grants um
at the uh federal and state level, we're
able to expand providing services beyond
the cooperative footprint into the the
rural areas surrounding the cooperative.
And with that, uh the area that we began
to serve uh grew significantly.
And so we continued to find
opportunities to to leverage grants and
and and build into areas as an edge out
so that we could provide
state-of-the-art services to our
neighbors that quite honestly we're in
great need of it. So that has kind of
been our focus when it comes to you know
traditional uh telecom services that
commitment to serve but you know beyond
that we also had a commitment to serve
other needs. Um we were early in taking
a look at how does it affect our
business and the community the
businesses in the communities we serve.
So we started building our ITMS MSP
service which now we're the the biggest
ITMS MSP between Kansas City and Denver
and we provide those services across the
state as well into as into the
neighboring states. Um telephone
companies got into broadband, telephone
companies got into television, you know,
just like cable companies got into
broadband. And so with that evolution,
we had local content media that we did.
And from that, we transitioned our media
marketing team basically into an ad
agency. Because our local communities
needed that and we found a niche by
helping other broadband providers
because we're a broadband provider. We
kind of understand, you know, what they
need to to do to be successful. So we've
had a really good opportunity to grow in
that aspect. You know carrier services
we created a network u um monitoring uh
system our knock and through that there
were others who needed network
monitoring. So we continue to expand
that. So we have knock customers and
kalia customers from you know the across
the entire US. And so we just had a
commitment to take things that were
important to how we operated and things
that were needed in our communities and
just kind of grow that and expand that.
But it's all because of having a a
dedicated team of truly amazing
professionals that care about our
customers and our communities. Because I
don't care who you are, without a great
team, you don't have a great company.
And I get to brag on my my NextTech team
as often as I can because without their
abilities, without their care, you know,
NextTech would be average. And we are
not average. And so, you know, we
continue to try and invest in our team
uh through training, through leadership
development. We've had the pleasure of
having uh families that are that grew up
with NextTech and we've got
multi-generational
uh examples of where parents worked at
NextTech and their and their you know
their adult kids are are now part of the
team. You know, I I think of like uh the
Ellis's, uh the Bascals, the Normandons,
uh the Walters, um even recently, um the
Dempseies and and the Schneiders, you
know, and there are others that that
have been part of the Next Tech family
and now the next generation is part of
the Next Tech family. And and that's
that's exciting and unique because in
our rural areas, we want our young
people to stay local and we want them to
have great jobs. And the fact that they
saw positive in where their parents
worked or their grandparents worked in
some cases is is a huge positive telling
sign that I think that you know we have
set a good example for for the young
people to to say hey this there is great
opportunity here and this company can
can give you that opportunity. So, you
know, I'm just my hats off to my team
because they're they're just fantastic.
>> Well, yes. I mean, when you think about,
you know, quality organization, you
think about retention. And so when you
have um people that have not just been
there for their entire careers, but
their family members, their kids, and
the next generations join, that's quite
a testament to um not only your
leadership, but uh it looks like, you
know, from what you've told me, you've
been standing on the shoulders of some
giants over the past. So it's it just
has a a great track record of strong
leadership for the last 75 years.
>> Yes, sir.
So that's not easy to do is to come in
and fill big I mean you've been there
quite a while and you've really taken
things to the next level. Um so one of
the things that um one of the questions
came in from our good buddy Steve is if
you could look past over the last 10
years you know whether it's policy or
technology or response to customer
demand is there anything that you would
have done differently?
Hm.
I would probably have built fiber faster
even. You know, we um were able to
finish building out our cooperative um
our very last customer in our
cooperative a couple of years ago and we
had acquired a small uh telecom uh
company in central Kansas and in a
couple of years we brought them all the
way fiber to the home. I would say um
probably building fiber a little bit
faster and and then finding even more
opportunities to expand that
connectivity outside of our current
service footprint.
>> So can you talk a little bit about I
mean you know you're in rural Kansas
right? I mean it seems to me like when
you go to the airport you drive five
hours to Denver. So it's there's a lot
of windshield time between you and
Denver. What has fiber done for the
businesses and the communities across
you know the areas 11,000 miles square
miles that you serve?
You know, one of the the things that I
think it makes a huge difference is um
you see a lot of communities that um are
in rural areas that have have gone away.
And I think that our
our uh bringing fiber connectivity to
the communities that we serve helped
them stay uh viable. Um,
when you look at what happened during
COVID and connectivity was more
important than it had ever been, you
know, I I look at how that affected our
communities and the fact that we did
have good broadband uh service and you
know it there are areas that we have
reached out with with uh fixed wireless.
is not our preference but to get people
connected we have done that you know in
the big scheme of things whenever we can
afford we can put a a project together
to get them transition to fiber that's
always our preference and that's what we
always work towards because at the end
of the day we have seen people move to
our rural community for remote jobs that
because of the connectivity that we have
they can work anywhere in the world. We
have seen education enhanced. We have
seen the ability for folks to use
technology in their businesses uh
whether it be small town businesses um
or whether it be uh rural agricultural
type businesses. And so having that
state-of-the-art connectivity truly
facilitates those communities and those
businesses and those homes to to be
connected to what is quite honestly the
most important connectivity medium which
is the broadband network, the internet.
you know, one, you know, the fact that
I've had the opportunity to work with
you for the last several years, uh, the
one thing that's clear is you're always
looking forward on what's the latest
technology. Hence, you know, you created
our, uh, precision agriculture working
group. You led our, um, AI and emerging
tech. Um, you've been, you know, on the
FCC, you know, um, precision egg
committee. um what you know when you
think about Kansas, you think about
precision egg, you think about AI, kind
of what is or what are you seeing as the
future of you know how we're going to
evolve with with this technology and why
is it important to get fiber to all
these places? Well, when you think about
AI and you think of data centers and you
think of the amount of data that is
going to continue to exponentially grow
that goes across our networks, you have
to have a fiber infrastructure to
facilitate that. You know, we have seen
uh data centers going in um all over the
metro areas. We have heard more and more
discussions about looking to rural
communities um for data center
locations. Now there's different types
of data centers. You've got the
hyperscaler data centers, you got the
large government, the large enterprise,
but you also have more edge type data
centers. So, you know, it will depend on
who is wanting to plant that data center
as to what type of fiber connectivity is
needed. when you're looking at
hyperscalers, the fat count fiber is
absolutely critical. And yet, you know,
we have used a data center for our own
ITMS MSP customers and our own
operations for for many years, and it's
it's not quite as dense. So, you're
going to have different flavors of data
centers. I think you're going to see
more fat count fiber needed in the
future, which is different than how we,
you know, engineered things in the past,
right? So uh those are things that I see
will be changing. Um AI is going to
enhance capabilities uh for workforce.
Um you know we have uh embraced AI and
are using it in multiple different ways
in our organization and you know there's
a there's excitement and there's fear
with that right uh for some people
there's a fear okay is this going to
take my job and you know others are like
you know what you know is this going to
turn into Skynet and and the Terminator
you know and and so you know really it's
it's our job to help them understand
this is to enhance what we're able to do
um as as a team, as an organization. Um
if we're able to to leverage AI and you
know be able to adapt and evolve how we
do things, processes, procedures, then
it allows us to grow and scale and serve
more customers and do it at the same
level of quality that we've always
expected from ourselves.
Yeah, I would think you know as we move
forward the work that you're doing and
especially when you think about AI
digital twins and precision a this is
exactly what will save family farms you
know being able to maximize productivity
and efficiency to allow these uh farms
to continue continue to grow. Um, is
that I mean what it's pretty hard to go
and take family businesses and convince
people to embrace technology. Is that
what you're seeing? Or do you think the
farms in your area are quick to embrace?
>> I would I would not say quick to embrace
by any means. I I would say yes. It it
is going to be kind of one of those
generational shifts. I do believe
because the the young folks that have
been going to the a schools are learning
about a tech and and and yet it's going
to depend on when they're the ones
getting to to make the decisions back
home at the the family farm, right? Um,
but I know some who haven't employed a
technology. And you know, I've got a
friend who who actually runs a, you
know, a farming business for seed for
thousands of acres, oneman operation,
right? Because he uses technology. Now,
he has custom cutters come in during
harvest time, but when you look at the
the rest of the year running the
business, he's using technology to be
able to do that. And it's it's quite
amazing to to see how that is a for
force multiplier when it comes to to
running a farm these days.
Um, one of the questions came from the
audience. Are you seeing much neocloud
activity in your service area? And what
about AI factories? Um, and you know,
how are they differing from largecale
hyperscalers and the way fiber you know
is deployed?
>> Really in in our footprint. I haven't
seen a lot of that. Um, we're keeping an
eye on it to see how that develops. um
with the fact that we go from the west
side to the central part of the state,
we we feel that we're positioned that if
those continue to advance, you know,
into to central Kansas or western
Kansas, we'll be ready to to help
facilitate it. But, um at this time,
that's still more in the conceptual
phase as opposed to the actual um
happening in in our footprint.
And another question that came in for
the audience is um you know I don't know
if the you know you since you serve
Kansas they're asking about city of
Lawrence uh is that something that you
guys would be able to provide fiber uh
they have quite a bit of need for that.
>> We are not uh serving in Lawrence. Um we
are as far east as we go is as Salina.
Uh so that's the central part of the
state. Um but uh you know I do know that
there are others that have been serving
um serving Lawrence. I don't know that
it's been fully built out. But you know
when we when we are building in a
community our goal is to to build out
the entire community and serve that
entire community and and that's what
we're progressing on right now in
Salina.
>> All right. So 75 years the big
anniversary is coming up. So, do you
have um something big planned for your
team?
>> Well, you know, it's going to be a
year-long celebration. Uh we like to
celebrate things and uh you know, in the
past, we've done things in, you know,
the summer uh pool parties in the
communities that we serve. Uh we've
created, you know, a history wall in
some of our locations to kind of show
folks how we've how we've grown the
organization and and evolved.
um got our employee meeting uh tomorrow
and so we're going to be excited to you
know kind of reminisce and and then look
forward um we've got a new location
that's uh we're going to have a ribbon
cutting in June for our Sunflower
building in Salina and uh so that's
going to be a new tech location in the
central part of the state. So, we're
excited about that and and really it's
just, you know, um celebrating with the
communities that we've been a part of
for that 75 years and uh we we keep
growing that list of communities. So,
that's that's been exciting.
>> So, Jimmy, you know, I lean on you every
day. you know, you're just uh your
leadership and you know, I know how much
time you put into the fiber broadband
association yet you're on all these
boards and I know that you are not
someone who just is passive on a board.
You're very highly active. Um so you're
in a lot of working groups, you're in a
lot of boards, you're traveling all over
the country and you're running a highly
successful um business. So, so how are
you able to do all this stuff?
>> Remember I was talking about that great
team. Without that great team and
without the support of a board that
feels that it's important for us to help
um um influence industry uh it wouldn't
be possible. you know, I I am blessed to
have an amazing uh team of senior
leaders at our company and you know,
quite honestly, they they make sure that
everything is working well and uh I feel
like I'm just uh fortunate to have uh
that position and that opportunity and
it allows, you know, me to take our
perspective and and share it with
others.
Well, I I you know, not only do you have
kind of the top level leadership um
advice and qualities, I really
appreciate your attention to detail as
we are doing investment strategies and
all the other things. So, you know, it
seems like you're all these areas and
boards and things that you're
participating. It it really provides a
lot of uh great expertise as well as,
you know, I don't know anybody that's
served in both the Navy and Army and
National Guard. So, you certainly
>> maybe I'm confused. I don't know.
>> Shirley keeps you in line. I know that
for sure. All right. So 75 years been
amazing.
>> Yes sir.
>> What's gonna happen? What is kind of
your vision for the next 10 years I'll
call it or five whatever horizon you
want to talk about for next tax and in
rural America.
>> Well you know we're going to create um
more transport routes to reach further
than where we currently reach. Um
creating new opportunities in in larger
uh metro areas. Um we are going to
continue to expand our ITMS MSP services
because as you are fully aware of cyber
security and data protection network
security that is is huge. Um we've seen
a lot of growth in our security
surveillance and access control
business. So we're expanding that beyond
the the Kansas footprint. um our knock
services continue to be something that
um ISPs uh needs, you know, help with
and we're able to to provide that help
and expanding how we help uh with our
creative team when it comes to uh online
presence um and marketing their
businesses and again just finding ways
to to continue
to to grow what we're already doing. But
I got one other new line of business
that's premature to to share right now
because we're still vetting all the
details out, but uh we'll be making an
announcement on that fairly soon.
>> Well, Jimmy, I you know, I love
everything you do and I appreciate
everything you do for me and the Fiber
Broadband Association and the industry
and I love meeting your teammates at
Nextech. They're amazing and appreciate
you everything you guys are doing for
rural Kansas. Also, all our audience
seem to keep sending messages and go
dogs. So,
>> yes, sir. I'm I'm still a big Georgia
Bulldog fan.
>> Yeah. So, everybody knows you pretty
well. Well, thank you very much, Jimmy.
And again, thanks our audience for
joining us. And next week,
>> I'm excited. Um, one of my favorite
guests, Carol Maddie, Mattie Consulting,
former FCC, is going to be here to
discuss mission accomplished or mission
abandoned, life after bead to uh, Carol
has incredible insights from all her
years and working in the Hill or not in
the Hill, but into FCC and other things.
And um, so you guys are not going to
want to miss that. So, we'll see you
guys next Wednesday and Jimmy, I will
see you long before then. So,